<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: blog_archive_project | mathias.github.com]]></title>
  <link href="http://mathias.github.com/blog/categories/blog-archive-project/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mathias.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-07-14T14:01:16-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mathias.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Gauger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git is full of win]]></title>
    <link href="http://mathias.github.com/blog/2008/03/28/git-is-full-of-win/"/>
    <updated>2008-03-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mathias.github.com/blog/2008/03/28/git-is-full-of-win</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(This post is part of my blog archiving project. This post appeared on
<a href="http://bytecodex.wordpress.com/2008/03/23/git-is-full-of-win/">bytecodex.wordpress.com</a>
on March 23, 2008.)</p>

<p>The blogosphere seems to be blowing up with regards to the SCM suite
<a href="http://git.or.cz/" title="http://git.or.cz/">git</a>. At least, the blogosphere
I frequent.</p>

<p>git is an open source project started by Linus Torvalds and currently
maintained by Junio Hamano, intended to replace the proprietary
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitKeeper" title="Wikipedia - BitKeeper">BitKeeper</a>
system that the Linux kernel project used. Like
<a href="http://www.monotone.ca/" title="http://www.monotone.ca/">Monotone</a> and
<a href="http://www.selenic.com/mercurial/wiki/" title="http://www.selenic.com/mercurial/wiki/">Mercurial</a>,
git is a modern decentralized revision control system that makes use of
cryptography. The ‘repo’ doesn’t live on one server, instead every local
copy on a developer’s machine is a full repo, with full version history.
Developers initially copy the repo from somewhere (also known as
branching or creating a clone) and make changes locally, commiting
changes to their local repo as they code.</p>

<p>The process of combining two branched repos in SCM is known as merging.
When developers are ready to share their changes, they can ‘merge’ their
work back into other developers’ trees, or others could pull down
changes from the developer’s local repo and work from there. Merging was
previously a time-consuming and frustrating task with other SCM tools,
but git needed to be able to merge the repos of the Linux kernel
developers fast. In fact, git makes it so much easier than previous SCM
tools to branch and merge both local and remote repos that developers
can keep several branches around locally for various changes to live in.</p>

<p>The best
<a href="http://www.mcl.iis.u-tokyo.ac.jp/eng_version/index.html">image I
found</a>
to represent this style of passing around changes has nothing to do with
version control, but gives a good idea if you think of ‘messages’ as the
changes:</p>

<p><img src="http://bytecodex.files.wordpress.com/2008/03/adhoc.jpg?w=269&amp;h=184" alt="adhoc.jpg" /></p>

<p>Because all the cool developers hack on laptops now.</p>

<p>Usually while riding on bullet trains.</p>

<p>Subversion &amp; CVS, on the other hand, use a centralized server that all
changes must be downloaded from and uploaded to; making concurrent work
possible. But a centralized server may be restrictive if a development
team is scattered across the globe (as in the Linux kernel team &amp; most
open source projects) rather than scattered across the cube farm. (As a
side note: git does allow for public repo servers, but that is a whole
‘nother topic.)</p>

<p>Best of all, <strong>git is fast</strong>. <a href="http://www.advogato.org/person/apenwarr/diary/371.html" title="Blog for apenwarr - Git is the next Unix">Faster than your
filesystem</a>,
in some cases. You can throw data in its repo &amp; <strong>10 years later it
ensures you get the exact same file out</strong>, due to cryptographic hash
checking. SCM tools of years past couldn’t vouch for the integrity of
your files, in fact checking in files was more likely to corrupt files
at some future point, rather than protect them.</p>

<p>I’m not going to go into all the features of git or why it’s faster,
there’s <a href="http://robsanheim.com/2008/02/22/learn-git-10-different-ways/" title="Panasonic Youth - Learn Git 10 Different Ways ">plenty of
resources</a> already.
If you’ve used Subversion (svn) in the past, then <a href="http://git.or.cz/course/svn.html" title="Git -SVN Crash Course">this
tutorial</a> is
probably your best bet.</p>

<p>Since this turned into more of an overview of git rather than covering
the two topics I had in mind when I started, look forward to two more
posts this week: one on <a href="http://github.com/">GitHub</a>, a git repository
hosting service, and <a href="http://atonie.org/2008/02/git-wiki">git-wiki</a>, a
wiki intended for personal use that checks its changes into a local git
repo.</p>

<p><a href="http://atonie.org/2008/02/git-wiki"></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Milwaukee DevHouse 1 Recap]]></title>
    <link href="http://mathias.github.com/blog/2008/03/19/milwaukee-devhouse-1-recap/"/>
    <updated>2008-03-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mathias.github.com/blog/2008/03/19/milwaukee-devhouse-1-recap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(This post is part of my blog archiving project. This post appeared on
<a href="http://bytecodex.wordpress.com/2008/03/19/milwaukee-devhouse1-recap/">bytecodex.wordpress.com</a>
on March 19, 2008.)</p>

<p><a href="http://rasterweb.net/raster/2008/03/18/milwaukeedevhouse1-wrap-up/">Pete Prodoehl has the
scoop</a>.
I don’t really know what to say about it. We all met up at Bucketworks
in Milwaukee with the intent to hack and hang out. I got there at 6PM
and left at around 5:30AM on the next day. It was quite the party.</p>

<p><img src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2106/2334180617_cb572b20ec.jpg?v=0" alt="devhouse
photo" /></p>

<p><em>(via <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/mattgauger/">my flickr</a>)</em></p>

<p>4braham started a twitter-events mashup project, and I unfortunately
wasn’t much help with it.. I guess I’m too easily distracted. Other
projects are detailed in Pete’s posts, I was actually out in the
Bucketworks Flow room and so missed most of what went on in the smaller
conference room.</p>

<p>The light table where we did our plotting:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3047/2334539597_e42fccdbe0.jpg?v=0" alt="light table at
bucketworks" /></p>

<p><em>(via <a href="http://flickr.com/photos/drydens/">ashe’s flickr</a>)</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fallacy: Startups don't work in the Midwest]]></title>
    <link href="http://mathias.github.com/blog/2007/12/07/fallacy-startups-dont-work-in-the-midwest/"/>
    <updated>2007-12-07T12:09:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mathias.github.com/blog/2007/12/07/fallacy-startups-dont-work-in-the-midwest</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(This post is part of my blog archiving project. This post appeared on
<a href="http://bytecodex.wordpress.com/2007/12/04/fallacy-startups-dont-work-in-the-midwest/">bytecodex.wordpress.com</a>
on December 04, 2007.)</p>

<p><strong>(aka I'll let you know when the Midwest stops sucking)</strong></p>

<p>Well, the title of this blog post is a little misleading: take for
example, <a href="http://37signals.com/">37signals</a>, which was the shining star
of Web 2.0 a year or two ago, contributed to the further web 2.0
explosion by releasing the Ruby on Rails framework free, and now has
become as ubiquitous and useful as internet infrastructure with their
products Basecamp, Backpack, Highrise, etc. <strong>37signals</strong> is, of course,
from Chicago, Illinois. Further, there are dozens of smaller, successful
Chicago startups that have carved out niches for themselves on the web,
like <a href="http://threadless.com/">Threadless</a>, another Chicago startup that
crowd-sources its products (successfully, I might add).</p>

<p><strong>But the problem I've always had is hearing visionaries like <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/startuphubs.html">Paul
Graham</a> or Joel Spolsky
saying you can only make startups work in big cities that are "startup
hubs,"</strong> like San Francisco (Silicon Valley) or New York City (where
finance lives). They're saying that the Midwest sucks too much to
create successful startups. Add Chicago as a "big tech city where
startups work" to the list, and you eliminate everyone in paragraph 1.
Chicago is, after all, a vastly different place than the majority of the
Midwest, both in attitude and population density.</p>

<p>The basic argument has become that some kid from a podunk town in
Wisconsin or Iowa can't start the next big thing. That's <strong>complete
and utter BS.</strong> Pardon the expression, but it's worth
repeating: <strong>It's BS.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Clever heading about why it can work:</strong></p>

<p><strong>The internet is, by design, decentralized.</strong> Judging by the number of
web-workers, co-workers, and freelancers out there today, one doesn't
need to be in the corporate headquarters to get the job done. The same
goes for startups. You can get broadband pretty much anywhere, and
that's the only requirement for the startup these days. Everything
else (hosting, support, infrastructure) is all distributed over the web,
can happen anywhere, and is available to customers all over the world.
You could work out of your cabana in the Caribbean as long as you have
broadband, and no one would be the wiser. In connection with this is our
next point:\</p>

<p><strong>Technology is cheap and readily available</strong>, too: laptops and servers
(or even virtual hosting) is all the technology you really need. The
cost of startups in this area has dropped to basically nothing. If
you're really cash-strapped, your hackers probably already have the
desktop or laptop they'll need to code, anyways. Virtual hosting is
probably the killer app here for startup hosting, with services like
Amazon's AWS (Elastic Cloud 2 and S3) leading the pack. (not
necessarily in terms of processing power, though.) You no longer have to
spec out several $10K servers and more expensive colo space when you
need to scale your web app these days, you just add more server
instances for a higher monthly fee. (And btw, yes, Milwaukee and Chicago
both have Apple stores to get your hackers their Macbooks.)\</p>

<p>As a corollary, <strong>all the software your startup needs (programming
languages, frameworks, databases, &amp; editors) is available online as
free, open source projects.</strong> If you're an expert in the technology,
and it lets you adapt quicker and innovate more than a big corporation
could pull off, you've can create a better product no matter where you
are geographically. As for your actual web app, you should probably
write it yourself, not outsource it or hire a contractor.</p>

<p><strong>You don't need a big team.</strong> Have a good idea and a friend to help
you? Good, you've got your team. You're filling all the roles of
developer, graphic designer, systems administrator, management, and
tester. No need for giant developer teams or marketing department.
You'll hire a lawyer and accountant as needed, but otherwise you're
set. It's also possible to outsource all your support in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/4-Hour-Workweek-Escape-Live-Anywhere/dp/0307353133/">4-Hour
Workweek</a>fashion,
or otherwise, a FAQ on your site probably does an even better job.</p>

<p><strong>Our cost of living is lower.</strong> If you're familiar with Paul
Graham's essay on <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/webstartups.html">The Future of Web
Startups</a>, you'll know
that he's already made the argument that all you need to create a
startup is a shared space for hackers to hack in, and web hosting. He
doesn't emphasize having a fancy office, but instead starting in an
apartment or house where bedrooms become offices and everyone lives
together, working day and night towards a common goal of success. The
problem of paying for expensive offices is then lowered. The difference
is that in California (or New York City), the cost of rent is
ridiculous. When success for your startup means just hanging on long
enough, usually only a few more months to get profitable or sell out,
your cost of living is important. So why pay for crazy-expensive living
arrangements in a big Victorian or Brownstone or San Francisco's
apartment prices? (think $1800/month studio apartments) A team, in say
Wisconsin, working from their cheap apartment can probably crank out the
same kind of work as these startups, for a fraction of the cost. Also,
everything else is cheaper out here, including food, so you can eat
pretty decent if you're willing to cook and still stay cheap. Then
again, you can still eat only ramen and Redbull if you want to.</p>

<p><strong>You only need an angel investor or two to start, or maybe no funding
at all.</strong> While VCs (Vulture Capitalists) will probably be unlikely to
fly out to see you in farmsville, you don't need them to start out. As
mentioned, startups are really cheap right now. So the amount you'd
need from an initial angel investor is very low. And believe it or not,
these potential angel investors are all over the place. They don't all
live in fancy mansions in Washington state or whatever. Even if you
can't find one, there's a good chance you can bootstrap your startup
yourself, and then get funding when you've already implemented your
million dollar idea and can demo to potential investors, or direct
interested parties to the working web app by handing them a card with
the URL.</p>

<p><strong>With the net, knowledge is hardly geographical.</strong> There's no secret
tricks known only to a few elite in Silicon Valley. You can have world
class hackers living anywhere and collaborating online as experts in
that knowledge domain. The Midwest can compete in expertise with
anywhere else. We do have smart and extremely talented hackers living
here.</p>

<p><strong>You don't have to take big risks</strong>, like moving across the country
for something that might fail. While people just out of college, the
typical startup founders, are capable of taking big risks like that, not
everyone wants to. Further, it becomes very costly personally if you do
end up failing and have to move back to Wisconsin with your tail between
your legs. Why not just stay in Wisconsin, see your family on the
weekends, and code just as hard as those guys in Silicon Valley?</p>

<p><strong>The Problems:</strong></p>

<p>Obviously, <strong>you miss out on the tech community</strong> if you're trying to
do a startup in the middle of nowhere. I'm often struck by how close
and efficient the "web 2.0" crowd is out in San Fran. For example,
watching Leah Culver (of Pownce) give a presentation on OAuth at the
Justin.tv office (despite the fact that we already have two startups
collaborating in this sentence) last week, I realized that planning for
OAuth that didn't happen over mailing lists or by some big regulatory
committee (cough, ICANN/W3C), but by going out to lunch together,
stopping by offices, and generally sharing the problems they had and
figuring out ways to solve them. You just can't get that kind of
concentrated knowledge and talent out here in Wisconsin, as awesome as
our tech community is, there's just not enough of us to make it work.
The community out there is evident when you hear some startup founder
twittering about dropping by another startup's offices to see what
they're doing, or everyone is at the same party / conference / barcamp
and the next week they've all created something new collectively.</p>

<p><strong>Wisconsin educations are not geared towards creating hackers or
entrepreneurs</strong>. A common argument for startup hubs is that the colleges
there are pumping out lots of very talented kids that are eager to break
into the startup scene. The inverse of this is that, in my experience,
Computer Science students in Wisconsin are getting the exact same kind
of courses, with probably the same level of quality (most likely better,
as you're unlikely to be getting taught by a TA at the smaller UW &amp;
private schools). But, I get the feeling when I talk to my CSCI
classmates is that maybe they are smart and know "about computers,"
but they're mostly just gamers or whatever that are in CSCI because
they wouldn't mind being tech support at a random company, or
wouldn't mind working on a cube farm for some corporation doing
"computer stuff." They're not in it because they're necessarily
passionate about programming or math or open source or changing the
world. They just want the stable, healthy paycheck from those kinds of
jobs. They're <a href="http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/archives/001002.html">the other
80%</a> of
programmers, if they end up programming at all after college. To make a
PG-ish generalization: Serious hackers seem to value their time, and in
Thoreau-ish fashion aren't willing to trade it for a paycheck if the
work isn't interesting or fulfilling enough. I should stress that this
is my perception the <strong>majority</strong> of CSCI students I know here in
Wisconsin, but I know a few that are shining examples of Midwest geek
hackerdom. Until we teach the same sort of attitude and expectations
that create Sergey Brins and Joel Spolskys, we're just making more
miserable Office Space drones who are in it for the paycheck and not for
passion.</p>

<p><strong>Public transportation sucks (aka, distances increase and people are
too spread out).</strong>When you've got to drive hours to cross state lines
to get to a BarCamp or ride the train from Milwaukee into Chicago to
catch the Reddit or Google party, you're less likely to go. So the
tech community is less likely to concentrate in one area for any period
of time, even an evening. Just as a personal example, Milwaukee has a
great professional group for web designers and developers, and their
meetings are less than an hour away if I were to drive, but so far I
haven't been able to make it to any of their meetings. I'm even
closer to downtown Chicago, but it's not practical to drive and the
train schedule is lousy at best. Even though San Francisco is a big
sprawling region, their public transportation, neighborhoods
concentrating the tech community, and constant tech events/conferences
trumps what we can pull off in the midwest any day.</p>

<h4>Time to prove them wrong.</h4>

<p>Go out there and make the next big thing. It won't cost you much,
it's not risky, and you'll see your friends and the tech community
every day on Twitter anyways. Work out of your apartment or on your free
time on the weekends. Get cheap entry-level virtual hosting, and see if
there's interest in your idea.</p>

<p>This is sort of my plan, as I find moving out to California currently
infeasible. It's uncertain whether any idea will turn out to be the
Next Great American Startup, but on the flip side, you're just as
likely to fail as your counterparts burning through cash in Silicon
Valley.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jogging the memory with Shoes]]></title>
    <link href="http://mathias.github.com/blog/2007/11/29/jogging-the-memory-with-shoes/"/>
    <updated>2007-11-29T12:09:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mathias.github.com/blog/2007/11/29/jogging-the-memory-with-shoes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>(This post is part of my blog archiving project. This post appeared on
<a href="http://bytecodex.wordpress.com/2007/11/29/jogging-the-memory-with-shoes/">http://bytecodex.wordpress.com/</a> on November 29, 2007.)</p>

<p>Today, I wanted to share my latest little one-night coding project. But
first, a little back story. I’ve been looking for a new Mac OS X GUI
text editor for the past couple of days because TextMate has once again
passed its free 30 day period for me. I don’t mind editing text purely
with keyboard commands in a terminal window, but sometimes it’s nice to
have a mouse and menus when you’re working with chunks of code. I’ve
read studies from Apple that while using only keyboard shortcuts seems
faster, in truth the mouse is quicker at the same task.</p>

<p>On the command line, I’m more likely to use vi than emacs, although I
know my way around both. So when I found <a href="http://code.google.com/p/macvim/">MacVim</a>, an “experimental”
Cocoa interface to vim, I knew I’d found my new editor on the Mac. I’ve
already tried all the free editors that worked on Mac OS X in the past,
including jEdit (too slow), Eclipse (really an IDE, and even slower),
Komodo/Smultron/etc., and even most of the for-pay editors (BBEdit,
aforementioned TextMate, and SubEthaEdit). MacVim really takes the cake,
as the vim core understands far more languages &amp; markups than TextMate’s
bundles; it’s as fast as one can perceive a program to be; and it adds a
GUI (gooey!) layer of goodness on top, including tabs, mouse-based
copy/paste/cursor positioning, and a full-screen editing mode to
eliminate distractions.</p>

<p>I’ve also been playing with <a href="http://code.whytheluckystiff.net/shoes/">Shoes</a>, a framework for making GUI apps
in Ruby. Shoes is the brainchild of Ruby super-hacker WhyTheLuckyStiff,
and I wouldn’t have heard about it without <a href="http://philcrissman.com/">Phil Crissman</a>‘s
<a href="http://twitter.com/philcrissman">twittering</a> about his interest in using it.</p>

<p>The super simple syntax in Shoes lets you lay out GUI components like
elements in a web page, and graphics/animations are easily added. Most
apps are as simple as:</p>

<pre><code>Shoes.app do
     stack :margin =&gt; 10 do
          para "Chunky Bacon!"
      end
end
</code></pre>

<p>But the real frustration is in the lack of documentation. There are a
handle of sample apps on the project’s SVN web repo and roughly 4
tutorials. The full documentation is currently being printed up as a
real-deal book by WhyTheLuckyStiff, and I didn’t feel coughing up the
$8+shipping to get a copy. (&amp; knowing Why, I wouldn’t understand
anything in it anyways). So, I’ve been playing around and doing a lot of
trial and error based on the sample apps to figure out functionality.
Luckily, Quicksilver makes the run-test-repeat loop very tight. (For the
interested, CMD-Space into QS, type “Shoes” TAB TAB, first three letters
of my Shoes’ script’s filename, ENTER &amp; it’s running. Having to launch
the .app rather than calling from the CLI is a problem unique to the OSX
version of Shoes. On Linux it’d be $ ./shoes App.rb )</p>

<p>My first little app was nothing more than adding file saving and opening
functionality to the sample edit.rb script, added color and formatting,
buttons, etc. and then modified it to catch a few more commands given
via keypress. Nothing too fancy, but it was a good way to figure out the
majority of Shoes’ internals. While it was a fun idea to entertain,
Shoes is not the ideal platform to develop a text editor in. Luckily, I
don’t have to, as I’ve got MacVim.</p>

<p>But maybe I could use a little tool to help me remember all the various
vi commands?</p>

<p><img src="http://bytecodex.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/shoes1.png?w=510-" alt="Shoes cheatsheet widget" /></p>

<p>Introducing my cheatsheet widget for vim in Ruby Shoes. It’s based off
the heavy cardstock “vi Quick Reference” sheet that everyone in my
vi-specific CSCI classes was issued (I imagine there’s an emacs
equivalent for classes where emacs is encouraged). Believe it or not,
the longest part of creating this app in Shoes was typing in all the
command hints off the physical copy &amp; thinking up multiple ways to implement
classes containing the data in Ruby. The reinforcement of forgotten vi command
skills in developing this widget in MacVim should be obvious.</p>

<p></p>
Using the drop-down allows you to access such diverse topics as:</p>

<p><img src="http://bytecodex.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/shoes2.jpg?w=510" alt="shoes2.jpg" /></p>

<p>It really does make a nice little app to have running off to the side,
and I’d argue that it was far simpler to create than an Adobe AIR app or
Apple Dashboard widget would have been with the same functionality.</p>

<p>Tomorrow, if suitably motivated I may extend it to read in any number of
.yml files containing ‘cheat sheet’ definitions, and add definitions
from any number of the PDF cheatsheets I’ve accumulated over the years
and never bothered to print out (glancing in my PDF dir, I spy PHP,
MySQL, sqlite3, microformats, and even, yes, Ruby &amp; Ruby on Rails
cheatsheets in there). Using graphics I’ll implement a simple ‘tab’
interface across the top and clean it up so it looks slick. (Red
background when you click on the Rails tab? With little Ruby icon
hovering there? Yes!)</p>

<p><img src="http://bytecodex.files.wordpress.com/2007/11/shoes3-1.jpg?w=510" alt="shoes3-1.jpg" /></p>

<p>Coding in Ruby is so much fun, it makes trivial things like this
interesting, and Shoes follows in that tradition.</p>

<p>Until next time, happy hacking.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
